<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<mstns:Metadata xmlns="http://tempuri.org/XMLSchema.xsd" xmlns:mstns="http://tempuri.org/XMLSchema.xsd" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
  <mstns:Data_Provider_Contact_Details>
    <mstns:Name>Anja Schmidt</mstns:Name>
    <mstns:Email>a.schmidt@ufz.de</mstns:Email>
    <mstns:Role>
      <mstns:Data_Creator>true</mstns:Data_Creator>
    </mstns:Role>
    <mstns:Affiliation>Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research - UFZ</mstns:Affiliation>
    <mstns:Country>Germany</mstns:Country>
    <mstns:Research_Group>
      <mstns:Research_Group>Experimental Interaction Ecology</mstns:Research_Group>
    </mstns:Research_Group>
  </mstns:Data_Provider_Contact_Details>
  <mstns:Dataset>
    <mstns:Project_or_Workshop_or_Thesis_Title>iDiv Ecotron</mstns:Project_or_Workshop_or_Thesis_Title>
    <mstns:Dataset_Title>The Aphitron experiment</mstns:Dataset_Title>
    <mstns:Short_Abstract>The Aphitron study was conducted from early February 2017 to mid-July 2017. In this experiment, 12 EcoUnits were split in two fully separated sections (--&gt; 24 independent subunits in total). In each subunit, two lysimeters - isolated from each other belowground, but connected aboveground - were each equipped with two herbs and two grasses, planted in monoculture patches, as well as one broad bean (Vicia faba) as phytometer. Both lysimeters were filled with sterilized soil and subsequently inoculated with bacteria, fungi, and nematodes. One of the two lysimeters was additionally equipped with larger decomposer organisms (earthworms and springtails). A low barrier with hook tape between the lysimeters prevented migration of soil fauna, while allowing aboveground organisms to move freely between plant stands. Besides soil fauna, the presence of herbivores (aphids) as well as the diversity and abundance of predator species (ladybirds) was manipulated.</mstns:Short_Abstract>
    <mstns:Keywords>nematodes, Vicia faba, Coccinella septempunctata, aphids, Centaurea jacea, Festuca pratensis, Bellis perennis, Holcus lanatus, BEF, multitrophic, network complexity</mstns:Keywords>
    <mstns:Data_Access_Policy>Open (CC BY 4.0)</mstns:Data_Access_Policy>
    <mstns:Extensive_Description_Of_The_Dataset>The dataset contains one file (Aphitron_data.csv). Content: Data from the iDiv Ecotron experiment “Aphitron” conducted in 2017 as a pilot study. This file uses the character encoding: UTF-8.

Description of variables:

- Variable name: EcoUnit
- Description: Number of EcoUnit (13 - 24)
- Data type: integer
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: Compartment
- Description: Name of section within an EcoUnit (=lysimeters), from A to D
- Data type: character
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: SubUnit
- Description: Two lysimeters within an EcoUnit that were connected aboveground, permitting the movement of aboveground animals
- Data type: string
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: Lysimeter
- Description: Combination of Compartment and EcoUnit
- Data type: string
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: NeighborSpecies
- Description: One of four possible (weed) plant species planted around the bean in the respective quarter of the lysimeter
- Data type: string
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: BGInverts
- Description: Belowground invertebrates - whether the lysimeter received earthworms and collembola (yes) or did not receive soil organisms other than nematodes (no)
- Data type: string
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: AGInverts
- Description: Aboveground invertebrates introduced into the connected compartments. There were 4 different treatments; aphids were present in all treatments except for NoInverts. Number of predator animals used per treatment: CoccinellaHigh (4 adult Coccinella septempunctata), CoccinellaLow (2 adult Coccinella septempunctata), NoInverts (no aphids, no predators), HerbivoresOnly (aphids present, but no predators)
- Data type: string
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: WeedDryMassEnd
- Description of the variable: Weed dry mass per species within a quarter of the lysimeter harvested, dried (70°C for 3 days) at the end of the experiment
- Data type: double
- Unit of measurement: g

- Variable name: BeanDryWeightEnd
- Description: Dry weight of bean phytometers at the end of the experiment. Some beans that had died could not be harvested and weighed; beans that were dead at the end, but could still be harvested, had likely already lost part of their biomass under good conditions
- Data type: double
- Unit of measurement: g

- Variable name: AphidDuration
- Description of the variable: Number of days that aphids were present on the bean phytometer, from first discovery until last discovery. Last discovery could be either the end of the experiment or the time a bean entered bad status and was not a suitable host for aphids anymore
- Data type: integer
- Unit of measurement: days

- Variable name: AphidMaxNumber
- Description: Maximum number of aphids counted at a given time point on the bean phytometer during the experiment. Aphid numbers were counted weekly between the introduction of aphids (2017-April-27) and harvest of beans with aphids (2017-June-6). Counts range from 1 to 100, where values of 100 could indicate much higher numbers of aphids
- Data type: integer
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: NematodeSpeciesRichness
- Description: Richness index = (S−1)/lnN; where S is the number of total genera in the community, and N is the number of identified individuals of nematodes in the community
- Data type: double
- Unit of measurement: NA

- Variable name: NematodeDensity
- Description: Density of nematodes per 100 g dry soil
- Data type: double
- Unit of measurement: N individuals/100g</mstns:Extensive_Description_Of_The_Dataset>
    <mstns:Data_Origin>Laboratory Experiment</mstns:Data_Origin>
    <mstns:Status_Of_The_Data_Collection>Completed</mstns:Status_Of_The_Data_Collection>
  </mstns:Dataset>
  <mstns:Persons_Associated_With_Dataset>
    <mstns:Name>Anja Schmidt</mstns:Name>
    <mstns:Email>a.schmidt@ufz.de</mstns:Email>
    <mstns:Role>
      <mstns:Data_Creator>true</mstns:Data_Creator>
    </mstns:Role>
    <mstns:Affiliation>Helmholtz Centre for Environmental Research - UFZ</mstns:Affiliation>
    <mstns:Country>Germany</mstns:Country>
    <mstns:Research_Group>
      <mstns:Research_Group>Experimental Interaction Ecology</mstns:Research_Group>
    </mstns:Research_Group>
  </mstns:Persons_Associated_With_Dataset>
  <mstns:Habitat>
    <mstns:Terrestrial>true</mstns:Terrestrial>
  </mstns:Habitat>
  <mstns:Taxonomic_Scope>
    <mstns:Animalia>true</mstns:Animalia>
    <mstns:Plantae>true</mstns:Plantae>
  </mstns:Taxonomic_Scope>
  <mstns:Temporal_Cover>
    <mstns:Date_of_first_Record>
      <mstns:Year>2017</mstns:Year>
      <mstns:Month>June</mstns:Month>
      <mstns:Day>6</mstns:Day>
    </mstns:Date_of_first_Record>
    <mstns:Date_of_last_Record>
      <mstns:Year>2017</mstns:Year>
      <mstns:Month>June</mstns:Month>
      <mstns:Day>6</mstns:Day>
    </mstns:Date_of_last_Record>
    <mstns:Temporal_Resolution>
      <mstns:Temporal_Resolution>Not Relevant</mstns:Temporal_Resolution>
    </mstns:Temporal_Resolution>
  </mstns:Temporal_Cover>
  <mstns:Spatial_Cover>
    <mstns:Coverage>Local</mstns:Coverage>
    <mstns:Locality_Names>iDiv Ecotron</mstns:Locality_Names>
    <mstns:Country>Germany</mstns:Country>
  </mstns:Spatial_Cover>
  <mstns:Additional_Information>
    <mstns:How_To_Cite_Dataset>Schmidt, A. (2021) The Aphitron experiment [Dataset]. iDiv Data Repository. https://doi.org/10.25829/idiv.3496-8-5695</mstns:How_To_Cite_Dataset>
    <mstns:Dataset_DOI_or_URL>https://doi.org/10.25829/idiv.3496-8-5695</mstns:Dataset_DOI_or_URL>
    <mstns:Publications_Based_On_This_Dataset>Schmidt, A. (in review) The iDiv Ecotron - a flexible research platform for multitrophic biodiversity research.</mstns:Publications_Based_On_This_Dataset>
    <mstns:Projects_That_Are_Related_To_This_Dataset>iDiv Ecotron</mstns:Projects_That_Are_Related_To_This_Dataset>
  </mstns:Additional_Information>
</mstns:Metadata>