<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<mstns:Metadata xmlns="http://tempuri.org/XMLSchema.xsd" xmlns:mstns="http://tempuri.org/XMLSchema.xsd" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema">
  <mstns:Data_Provider_Contact_Details>
    <mstns:Name>Florian Schnabel</mstns:Name>
    <mstns:Email>florian.schnabel@idiv.de</mstns:Email>
    <mstns:Role>
      <mstns:Data_Creator>true</mstns:Data_Creator>
      <mstns:Data_Manager>true</mstns:Data_Manager>
      <mstns:Data_Owner>true</mstns:Data_Owner>
      <mstns:Primary_Contact>true</mstns:Primary_Contact>
    </mstns:Role>
    <mstns:Affiliation>iDiv</mstns:Affiliation>
    <mstns:Country>Germany</mstns:Country>
    <mstns:Research_Group>
      <mstns:Research_Group>Other-specify</mstns:Research_Group>
      <mstns:Other-Specify>DFG International Research Training Group TreeDì</mstns:Other-Specify>
    </mstns:Research_Group>
  </mstns:Data_Provider_Contact_Details>
  <mstns:Dataset>
    <mstns:Project_or_Workshop_or_Thesis_Title>TreeDì project P3G</mstns:Project_or_Workshop_or_Thesis_Title>
    <mstns:Dataset_Title>Cumulative growth and stress responses to the 2018–2019 drought in a European floodplain forest: Data and code on tree growth and δ13C responses to drought</mstns:Dataset_Title>
    <mstns:Short_Abstract>Data and code needed to reproduce the 1) growth response, 2) δ13C and 3) drought legacy analyses of the paper: Schnabel et al. Cumulative growth and stress responses to the 2018–2019 drought in a European floodplain forest.</mstns:Short_Abstract>
    <mstns:Keywords>climate change, hotter drought, forest ecology, dendroecology, tree rings, growth resistance, δ13C, cavitation resistance, stomatal control, temperate forests</mstns:Keywords>
    <mstns:Data_Access_Policy>Open (CC BY 4.0)</mstns:Data_Access_Policy>
    <mstns:Extensive_Description_Of_The_Dataset>The database contains the data and code needed to reproduce the 1) growth response, 2) δ13C and 3) drought legacy analyses of the paper: Schnabel et al. Cumulative growth and stress responses to the 2018–2019 drought in a European floodplain forest. Under Review in Global Change Biology. 

In this work, we examined tree growth and physiological stress responses (increase in carbon isotope composition; Δδ13C) to the consecutive drought years 2018–2019 using tree-rings of dominant tree species in a Central European floodplain forest. We compared observed responses to former single drought years and calculated drought legacy effects in tree growth (quantified as observed growth minus predicted growth as expected based on climate in the year after the drought event). 

The dataset comprises data on tree growth (raw and detrended tree-ring width; data_trw_rwi.csv), δ13C (data_d13C.csv) and on drought legacy effects (data_legacy_effects_SPEI_12.csv). Next, the dataset comprises the corresponding .R scripts for the growth response and δ13C analyses (Analyses_growth_d13C.R) and for the drought legacy analysis (Analysis_legacy_effects.R) presented in the paper. Details on the data analyses can be found in Schnabel et al. 2021. Data and code are provided as .csv and .R files encoded as UTF-8. Missing values are identified as "NA". 
Metadata, including detailed variable descriptions, measurement units and data type is included in Metadata_Schnabel_et_al_growth_d13C.txt. 

## Archive content:
Schnabel_et_al_2021_data_code_growth_d13C.zip  

File names: 
data_trw_rwi.csv data_d13C.csv 
data_legacy_effects_SPEI_12.csv 
Analyses_growth_d13C.R 
Analysis_legacy_effects.R
Metadata_Schnabel_et_al_growth_d13C.txt</mstns:Extensive_Description_Of_The_Dataset>
    <mstns:Data_Origin>Field Survey</mstns:Data_Origin>
    <mstns:Status_Of_The_Data_Collection>Completed</mstns:Status_Of_The_Data_Collection>
  </mstns:Dataset>
  <mstns:Persons_Associated_With_Dataset>
    <mstns:Name>Christian Wirth</mstns:Name>
    <mstns:Email>cwirth@uni-leipzig.de</mstns:Email>
    <mstns:Affiliation>Systematic Botany and Functional Biodiversity, University of Leipzig</mstns:Affiliation>
    <mstns:Country>Germany</mstns:Country>
  </mstns:Persons_Associated_With_Dataset>
  <mstns:Habitat>
    <mstns:Terrestrial>true</mstns:Terrestrial>
  </mstns:Habitat>
  <mstns:Taxonomic_Scope>
    <mstns:Plantae>true</mstns:Plantae>
  </mstns:Taxonomic_Scope>
  <mstns:Additional_Information>
    <mstns:How_To_Cite_Dataset>Schnabel, F., Purrucker, S., Schmitt, L., Engelmann, R. A., Kahl, A., Richter, R., Seele-Dilbat, C., Skiadaresis, G., Wirth, C. (2021) Cumulative growth and stress responses to the 2018–2019 drought in a European floodplain forest: Data and code on tree growth and δ13C responses to drought. iDiv Data Repository.</mstns:How_To_Cite_Dataset>
  </mstns:Additional_Information>
</mstns:Metadata>